## Federico Fabio Frattini

☑: frattinf@tcd.ie☑: @FedFabFrat□: +353872172669

**(b)**: Personal Website **in**: Linkedin Profile

I am a PhD candidate in Economics at Trinity College Dublin, where I am working on research projects related to political economics and the economics of crime, with an applied-micro approach and a focus on causal inference. I am also passionate about coding, programming languages and statistical software. I am curious, a hard worker, with an analytical mindset prone to problem-solving. I am based in Dublin but I am planning to relocate to Italy.

### Education

Ph.D., Economics, Trinity College Dublin, September 2018-(Expected) September 2022

Thesis title: "Essays in Political Economics"

Supervisor: Nicola Mastrorocco

M.Sc., Economics, Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, 2015-2017

Supervisor: Massimo Bordignon

B.Sc., Economics and Management, Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, 2011-2015

Supervisor: Salvatore Piccolo

### Work Experience

Trinity College Dublin, September 2018 -(Expected) September 2022

- Guest lecturer:
  - · Workshop in Big Data and Machine Learning (M.Sc., Ph.D.) at Maynooth University, Spring 2022.
- Teaching Assistant:
  - Introduction to Microeconomics (M.Sc.), Fall 2021, val.: 5/5. Topics in Political Economy (M.Sc.), Fall 2019, 2020, val.: 4.75/5.
  - · Development Economics (M.Sc.), Spring 2020. · Emergence of Macroeconomic Policy (M.Sc.), Spring 2020, val.: 4.3/5.
  - · Long Run Development (M.Sc.), Fall 2019, val.: 5/5. · Introduction to Economic Policy A/B (B.Sc.), 2018-2019, val.: 4.11/5.
- Research Assistant.

**SAS**, May 2018 - August 2018

• Training Analytical Consultant: Organizing and delivering classes on SAS Base programming language.

# Skills, Technologies and Languages

#### Research Skills:

 $\cdot \ \, \text{Data management.} \cdot \text{Data scraping.} \cdot \text{Data visualization.} \cdot \text{Micro-Econometrics.} \cdot \text{Causal inference.} \cdot \text{Machine Learning.}$ 

#### Soft Skills:

 $\cdot \ \, \text{Critical thinking.} \cdot \text{Problem solving.} \cdot \text{Detail-oriented.} \cdot \text{Independent/team-work.} \cdot \text{Good communication.} \cdot \text{Project management.}$ 

Software: STATA (fluent), Python, R (intermediate), SQL, QGIS, SAS, Office (basic).

### Languages: Italian (native), English (fluent).

Research Projects

Setting an example: political leaders' cues and health behavior in the early stages of the COVID-19 pandemic in Mexico, with Bruno Morando and Luciano Ayala, Latin American Policy (2021)

- How do political leaders' cues affect citizen behavior regarding a new and complex issue?
- We combine local electoral and mobility data within the context of Mexico in the early stages of the Covid-19 pandemic.
- We exploit an event-study type of analysis. Citizens' geographic mobility in pro-government municipalities was higher than in cities where support for the president was less strong.

• Our results are driven by cities with higher TV and internet penetration.

#### Simultaneous elections and electoral outcomes: evidence from Italy

- I Investigate the impact that same day national-local elections have on the local electoral stage.
- I employ a difference-in-differences estimation design, comparing same-day and not same-day election, within the Italian
  context. Voters' participation, political participation and competition increase. Right local parties gain in term of local votes
  share.
- I then focus just on same day national-local elections only. A relevant % of municipalities prefers left (right) at the local level and right(left) at the national one. Voters behave as such to balance government's levels to then have balanced policies.

#### Organised crime, public procurement and firms, with Decio Coviello and Nicola Mastrorocco

- What is the impact of criminal organisations on the legal economy?
- We employ a difference-in-differences estimation design within the South-Italian setting. We exploit the staggered enforcement of a law that allows the national government to dissolve Mafia-colluded local governments.
- We combine highly detailed public procurement and firms balance sheet data.
- Cities colluded with the Mafia exhibit lower rebates and higher discretionary selection procedures. The results vary depending
  on the macro-procurement category considered and the party affiliation of the local colluded government.
- Firms that win public contracts in cities colluded with the Mafia exhibit higher profits.

#### Social capital and the power of mafia, with Francesca Calamunci

- What is the long-term effect of organized crime presence on social capital?
- We collect contemporary data that proxy for social capital, and historical measures of Mafia presence. We inspect two scenarios within the Italian landscape.
- First, we focus on the island of Sicily. We run linear and instrumental variable regressions. We find that the long-term exposure to the Mafia decreases the development of social capital.
- Second, we focus on the centre-north regions of Italy. We exploit a law that forced Mafia members to resettle in this macro-area. We find a set of mixed result that need further understanding.

#### Organised crime and human capital, within-city evidence from Italy

- What is the effect of organised crime on human capital?
- I investigate this question in the Italian setting, focusing on a set of cities with high prevalence of organised crime.
- I exploit OCR to measure from the DIA's maps the presence and the names of the gangs within this set of cities.
- I plan to exploit text analysis to re-construct the traditional presence of these gangs, as well as the level of competition within
  a district of a city.
- I plan to combine this novel dataset with human capital data from INVALSI, and estimate a difference-in-differences model.

## Awards and Fellowships

Economics Department Scholarship, Trinity College Dublin, 2018-2020 2020 Government of Ireland Postgraduate Scholarship, Irish Research Council, 2020-present

#### Interests

Sports, with a particular interest on basketball and football. Travelling, videogames and playing guitar.

#### References

Prof. Nicola Mastrorocco (supervisor) Economics Department Trinity College Dublin n.mastrorocco@tcd.ie Prof. Gaia Narciso Economics Department Trinity College Dublin narcisog@tcd.ie Prof. Marvin Suesse Economics Department Trinity College Dublin marvin.suesse@tcd.ie